[music]
Heat. Heat. [music]
Welcome to Mental Health Monday. This is
the first mental health Monday of 2026.
So, welcome. We are so happy to see all
of you here this evening. Good to see
you, Dr. White. I was just telling you
when we went on, I haven't seen you
since last year. [laughter]
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, I can hear you.
>> Yeah. I hope you're having a great new
year and um we made it just in time
because I was I was projecting February
>> before Yeah, just in time. January is
almost over. I was making appointments
with clients for next week and I'm like,
it's already going to be February. We we
already are in the second month of 2026.
Time really does
>> fly by so fast.
>> So, it really reminds you to be
intentional about your time. I gather
you've been enjoying some time with the
grandbabies.
>> Yes. We had our third grandchild, second
grandson. So, that was exciting. Um,
it's just I remember when our first
grandchild was born and it was like, oh,
well, we're grandparents, but you know,
we're grandparents of like one. And for
four, let's see, no, not for four. uh
for three years it was just one and then
there was two and it's like okay we're
getting we're becoming like more even
more grandparents you know what I mean
becoming more of grandparents I should
say and then with the third it's like
wow we're super duper grandparents
[laughter]
>> we're all in now
>> we're all the way in and that's just
with one child having children so
imagine when the others start it's going
to be a [clears throat] lot I was even
doing Christmas this year I'm like
buying gifts and I'm like, "Okay, this
is getting deeper and deeper. Wait till
everybody, you know, everybody's going
to they're going to have to start just
getting one gift each. [laughter]
>> One gift,
>> not two."
>> We've suspended the whole, you know,
we've suspend. We're just like, "Look,
man, let's make it about food and having
a good time."
>> That too. Or I've been trying to
convince them like, "Let's just go on a
destination, no gifts. Let's just put
the money into like going somewhere.
It's better."
>> Absolutely.
>> Yeah. Absolutely.
>> I think that's fun. But yes, guys,
welcome. We're happy to have you here.
Please let us know where you're viewing
from. Clint, I saw I saw even before we
went on, you were the first one.
And Clint, I've been seeing you all over
the place. Like, um, two weeks ago when
we did our tin horns, you were there.
You were active in that chat. You were I
see you, of course, on the church
service. I see you all over the place.
That's great.
>> And I was in your I was in your state,
uh, Clint. I was in Texas. That's where
our grandchildren live. So,
know all about Texas. Hope everyone is
staying warm as well. This is like I
mean I don't know what it's like in
California. I haven't even looked at the
weather. Matter of fact, I talked to
Ammer earlier and they were at the beach
yesterday. So I'm assuming you guys are
chilling.
>> It's there's a crisp chill in the air
like so. But like when I when I walk
outside and I'm like this is what's
considered winter and it's like 68
degrees.
>> Don't stop it. You're in my state and
it's I don't stop. You're you're you're
tempting me.
>> Nothing. We've got nothing to complain
about. Nothing.
>> You have nothing to complain about. It's
freezing here in Tennessee. Tennessee is
only Nashville's only two hours away and
they're having like like it feels like
zero like I don't know one two degrees
something like that. And we're not that
bad, but we're we're cold. We're pretty
cold.
>> Well, we have people from all over. We
have people in Florida. I'm I'm sure
they're not feeling the cold either.
Welcome from Marco in Florida. We have
Well, brother Tennessee, tell us how
cold it is in Tennessee.
>> We're good.
>> Uh, good to see you here.
>> Silia from Jamaica from Jamaica. I'm
sure you're warm there, but welcome to
Mental Health Monday. Let us know if
this is the first time, guys. We want to
know if we have any first timers. Uh,
today also Oregon.
>> Yeah, Oregon. It's very cold.
>> Yes. Very good to see all of you here.
I'm excited about tonight's this evening
whenever you're watching this the topic.
Um because I don't think we've ever just
focused on on men and their mental
health. We have not done that. And this
is
>> starting our fourth year of doing mental
health Monday. Can you believe that?
>> That's wild. It just it just shows you
how much time is flying. Um
>> Yes. Yes. Courtney, [clears throat]
Georgia, I'm sure, is freezing because
Alabama's freezing and Nashville's I
mean Tennessee is freezing. So, we're
all freezing in the south here. I
haven't stepped outside to be honest.
Um,
all I haven't stepped outside since
Friday. [laughter]
>> Well, you probably
the house because it's just been cold
and Yeah, it's
>> And you're also probably doing online
therapy, right?
>> Yeah, all my Yes. All my clients are
online right now. Even if they were in
person, I was like, you're online this
week or for right now. It's cold. Until
it warms up, it's Yeah, it's just been
so cold. But it will be warming up.
Well, mid I don't know. This week's
going to stay pretty cold for us as I
look at the forecast. [clears throat]
But I think by the end of the week, it's
going to start warming up.
>> So, that's good. Good to see all of you.
Got Trinidad and Tobago and Georgia. And
I said Georgia, but another Georgia
part. That's great. Very good to see
everyone. Like again, we're excited
about the topic. Um I'm excited about
the topic. Going to take a deep dive
into that this evening. I had mentioned
to you Dr. White about a lot of the
things that are happening. [sighs] Those
we know we have an international
audience. So those who are not in the
US, you are probably not as impacted.
Even though when I travel around the
world, a lot of people say um whatever
the US is going through, it affects the
rest of the world just because of how
things work. Meaning, uh they either see
what we're going through and get like
kind of stressed out if we're going
through something because it affects
them. Um [clears throat] I had a friend
from Australia say, "If um
if America sneezes, Australia catches a
cold." and he was really talking about
the economy and stuff like that, but I
think it's a good analogy like the world
does watch what we do. They do.
>> Yeah. Yeah. A lot of stress going on
right now.
>> A lot of stress and we just wanted to
this is not what the whole program is
about. It's it's definitely for about
men and their and men's mental health uh
today. But uh there is a lot of stress
there. you know, we would be
not being as empathetic as we could be
to think that um you know, we don't have
people that watch us and that are
affected by um immigration. We have
friends or families that may not be um
here legally. And there's a lot of
stress over that, especially what they
what we see on the news and what how
things are happening um in regards to
ICE and what's happening in Minnesota
right now. And even if we're even as
American citizens, we're stressed
because two people who have passed who
um where their life was taken were US
citizens.
>> Um and so that's stressful.
>> No, no question. No question. I don't I
obviously the the woman that was um the
woman that was unalived I think they
like to say in this
>> um you know internet uh context
>> right
>> I that was a more [clears throat] well
publicized you know situation I guess
there's a more recent uh incident that
occurred I don't watch the news so
>> smart so that you're not stressed going
into their clients honestly
>> like but it it's just such a focus on on
on really just hair raising things and
in this big world I know there are good
things that I know they're heartwarming
stories and I just don't I don't hear
that celebrated uh the people
>> achieving amazing overcoming odds and
doing amazing things with their life
it's almost like that's just completely
disregarded and instead it's you, you
know, there's a there's a cop chasing a
car and there's I mean [laughter] like
they'll literally stop programming to
feature that.
>> And I'm thinking to myself,
>> you're going to en encourage other
people to to to want their 15 minutes of
of fame rather than let's let's not
>> let's not feature those kind of things.
Let's feature the stuff we want to see
more of, you know.
>> Yes. Because there's yes, there are good
things that are happen uh around this
world. But you're right, that's not uh
sensational and people don't really want
to
>> they don't hone in on that. Um I know my
mom lives with us now and so sometimes
if I feel like the news has been on a
lot that day and because I don't want
her to get too anxious and the news has
been just very negative about things,
I'm like, "Okay, that's enough. We're
switching into I switched to some family
program. Like we're not watching any
more of that." And it and it's good
because as the news keeps going and
going and going, she does get a little
bit more
>> just anxious just from watching it. But
we know that um that many people are um
some of the things that we take for
granted and don't worry about every day.
Uh people who either are here illegally
or have family or friends are here
illegally and um are good people working
hard. just
almost want to say minding their own
business and just not causing issues uh
for the community. Um they live on
eggshells and this situation does not is
not helping. So, just guess we wanted to
say that um we are we do care and we're
empathetic to everything that is
happening around the country right now
because it is very
uh it's actually very scary because like
I said the two that were unalived were
American citizens and they weren't
breaking any laws. So, it's kind of
scary.
>> 100% kind of
>> scary very mental health person.
>> Yeah. Um, but we are here this evening
to talk about [clears throat] men's
mental health. And I think the segue to
that just kind of flows and just flows
because
I don't know as a you've been a mental
health professional longer than I have.
Um but in the time that I have been um
an um [clears throat] a mental health
provider,
I have you know seen like I think really
before I became a therapist, I did not
really understand
the stress that men can feel the
responsibility that even society just
like it's just like you're a man. you're
born with this amount of responsibility
just because you're a man. Um, and and
it wasn't until I became a therapist
that I realized this is a lot to carry.
>> On top of
the fact that
we also then tell you don't show any
emotions, don't cry, don't be a baby,
don't act like it's hard. You put those
two things together and it's like
mercy. the the the the I mean you can
speak you're a man so you can speak of
it to it a little bit better than I can
but I really started to have empathy
for the first time in my adult life for
men and just what you guys face um just
being living in society. Go ahead Dr.
White. Well, you know, it's interesting
because we were we were studying David
um in a Sabbath school class and uh one
of the things that I came to realize is
how
when you're a leader, people want you to
make the big important decisions
which requires you to distance yourself
from your humanity while at the same
time being humane.
And I find it really relevant
with with being a man where you're
called upon to be a gentle man even when
you're working on some really like
challenging situations that are calling
the brutess out of you,
>> right?
>> But there's a gentleness that you're
always expected to not completely let go
of. Mhm.
>> And there's this kind of pushpull that
you sit in the middle of
>> and and it it can be stressful and there
can be there can be very few settings
where you get to articulate
your experience.
>> Yes.
>> And the struggles of it. There can be
very very few settings where you're
heard, you're validated, and
what you shared is not weaponized
against you.
>> Yes. Absolutely.
Absolutely. Well, we want to look and
[laughter] let me tell you guys that
also you are a part of this
conversation. If you have questions or
comments, I think we have one at least a
comment. Um, please put them in the
chat. We want you to be a part of our
discussion.
um this evening for sure. So, let's look
at some of the things that that you know
men go through with their uh mental
health. Again, this may be something
especially for women. This is why I'm
hoping in the advertisement we said this
program is for everyone because I think
it's important for us as as women to
learn and understand and to um just
appreciate what in a in a way that we we
can have empathy uh for men and have
understanding appreciate in that way. um
especially even and also raising young
young men and just to prepare them um
for what how what society can bring to
them um and the standards that society
holds them to that they don't have to to
hold to that standard because I I have
had so many
men cry on my couch I do tell health too
or on the screen
um that have never felt comfortable
enough to just really release in that
way. And when they do and they feel
heard, they feel so much better.
>> Yeah. 100%. So the first [clears throat]
the first thing that we were wanting to
talk about this evening is exactly this
this pushpull this
>> the fact that men are called to be
strong and stoic,
>> right? But in order to really achieve
that, it requires you to kind of stuff
your emotions down. Well, when you
condition yourself to stuff your
emotions down, of course, you might not
even be aware of what it is that you're
experiencing. And psychology 101
>> identifies the fact that when you're
trying to heal, an important part of is
naming what you're going through.
>> And if you're conditioned to stuffing it
down,
>> you can't even name it. And if you can't
even name it, then sometimes you can't
even heal. And this is why you find men
kind of
[clears throat]
>> shying away from seeking mental health.
Uh moving away from language like I need
help. Like that's just that's just seen
as a failure
>> like and weak. And and and part of the
call is you've got to be perceived as
strong. And so, of course, we have these
warped ideas of what is strength and
what is weakness, but you can see why
society doesn't really set us up
>> to obtain mental health care. And for
the men that do, it has for a long time
um kind of made them feel like they're
they're weak in doing that.
>> You know, fortunately, that's changing.
>> Yeah. But [clears throat] that's been
the the the past experience that I've
observed as it relates to men embracing
mental health.
>> Yes. Well, there's a great question here
[clears throat]
uh that Marco is asking. It says, "I try
to give my emotions to God, but I still
feel pain. Do you have advice for me?"
>> Man, wouldn't it be cool if they could
like if they could come on live?
>> Yes. And uh and because because then he
could unpack that like
>> I know
>> what does that mean?
>> We're gonna figure that out because I
feel like we could we're gonna figure
that out.
>> That would be so hot. Um where like they
can like Amra could even have them
waiting in the background. But yeah.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. And then we just bring them up
like Amber just be like but yeah it's
like
>> what does that mean? I give my pain to
God. You know what is that like a prayer
session? But it'd be really cool for
Marco to uh crystallize what that
exercise looks like in terms of how he
gives his pain uh to God because
you and I both know
it's we we talk about pain as if it's
like a little like it's this glass, you
know, like okay, like this glass. Hey,
um, get get that behind you or deal with
your pain or move on from it or give it
away.
>> And you and I know from that book, The
Body Keeps the Score,
>> right?
>> It's so integrated.
>> It's so integrated. How do you
externalize it? Mhm.
>> Uh and so yeah, I would love to hear
what is your process for saying you're
handing it off um to God because that
sounds pretty challenging.
>> Um now what do I think he's saying? Um I
think he's saying like he prays about
it,
>> right?
>> And he tries to deal with it with God.
>> Let me see what is he saying. It's been
hard for me to deal with my emotions as
part of the family ignores me and it
makes it worse that I don't really have
friends. I did them wrong, but I feel
like they did wrong, too. So, it's kind
of like this natural backwards and
forwards that you would expect. Yes.
Like in prayer and thinking and praying
[clears throat] Bible verses, especially
Psalms.
>> You know what's interesting about the
Psalms? Like when you read the Psalms,
you're getting an intimate portrait of
that person's experience,
>> right? And
it it can be powerful because you're
seeing
David raw like
>> you're seeing unedited like and and I
think he's modeling what we're supposed
to do. And so I think the key is to not
stop at just letting it be modeled, but
then you have your own prayer. Um,
there's this line in Psalms where David
says, "I want to bathe my feet
[clears throat] in the blood of my
enemies."
>> So much for the 23rd Psalm. So much for
Psalm 91. Like that is not a gentle
sounding idea. But I tell you what it
is.
>> It's unedited.
>> This is unedited speech. And sometimes
that can be so therapeutic to have a
setting where you don't have to edit.
You don't have to make it sound neat.
You don't have to be politically
correct,
>> right?
>> This is an unedited intimate
communication. And that can be so
cathartic. It can be so healing.
>> He's saying, he says, I don't, he said,
but I do repeat the painful thoughts in
my head, so maybe I'm [clears throat]
not really giving it all to God. And I
want to just, um, just go on with what
you're saying, uh, Dr. white that you
know Marco you give it to God and then
it's like you give it to God but then
your human nature picks you can pick it
back up and with you and you're so wired
meaning um you've been living with this
pain or for I don't know how long but
usually for a while and so you're used
to those negative painful thoughts and
sending and letting those thoughts um
just go automatically. And so when you
give it to God, that is good. And then
when you you have to make a daily
decision or a momentby-moment decision
to to begin the process to start
rewiring your mind give, you know, not
going from automatic thoughts to start
um challenging those thoughts and
reframing those thoughts so that your
feelings can be different. um because
about the I don't know your personal
situation completely. I just know
there's hurt and there's pain and
there's stress from just being a male in
this society. So your your you know the
thoughts that you have um that your
automatic thoughts that you have in your
mind will definitely affect the way that
you feel. Even though you went to God in
prayer, there's still a momentby-moment
decision that you have to you have to
make. And that's a process.
100%. Like and and I think but that's
that's exactly it like what is your
process?
>> What is what is what is going to be your
process your system for how you're going
to really and truly heal?
Um like because I I think that's that's
and and that's where sometimes a
professional support can come in. And
it's not like cuz it's like
>> like Marco is like but at the end of the
day am I really giving it? Um and that's
why that's that's where I began with
what what are you what are you giving
and how would you be giving it more so
than just labeling it and kind of having
that conversation with God. Um, but
that's where you can see the the the
power of professional support
actually
helping you identify a process that
truly heals.
>> Yes, absolutely. And I would say even I
like what where you're going and I like
Marco. I love your questioning and what
you're you're revealing here because I
think it's so important um for Christian
men, Christians in general like to know
that uh what you're doing is the right
thing. you giving it over to God and you
assist you getting some mental health um
counseling or assistance with that is
not bad and it doesn't mean that you're
lacking faith because I've had
Christians ask if I'm praying but I and
still feel like I need to go to therapy
or go to therapy am I lacking faith in
God and no you're not
>> not at all not and I mean you see so
many of the examples in scripture
where people have crises of faith where
people are asking those very questions.
Marco also raised another very important
issue that a lot of men are dealing with
and that is the feeling of isolation.
>> Like when we look at our women
counterpart, oh my goodness, they kill
it in this area. Like, you know, my
wife, she's got her friends and they got
their networks and okay, we're gonna
celebrate this, we're gonna celebrate
that. And they're on these group chats
and they do run circles around us as men
as far as like associating and getting
together with on some regular basis
>> and even even just sheer achievement
like the the road of leadership, the
road of entrepreneurship, it's a lonely
road. It can be.
>> Yes. It's like even if you wanted to
associate with your friends,
the there is a demand when you're really
setting out to be excellent, there's a
pulling away that is required.
>> That's lonely.
>> You you have to sacrifice
going to this social event and that
social event and and then there's the
mere fatigue, you know.
Um but the consequence is sometimes an a
very undesired isolation
>> uh which magnifies the difficulty of the
healing that can so often occur in
community.
>> Right.
Absolutely. Just to remind you guys,
we're taking your questions and comments
for this evening. Uh we're just talking
about men and their mental health and
really um it's we have found as mental
health professionals and just really
living life that it is difficult uh for
men just because the way society sets
things up and the pressure
um that is on men. And I want to say
this, you know, I kind of started this
line of thinking that I want to this
comment that I'm going to make. It
really um started again when I became a
therapist, but just the pressure of
knowing I made my daughter laugh today
when I told her this. And I don't know
if this has happened to you, Dr. White,
but I'm going to tell it. I don't care.
I'm just going to tell it anyway. It's h
it's happened to me to where there's
been situations
that people bring into my office and
it's so
challenging and difficult that my first
thought, this is my first human thought.
Everyone don't laugh because I I
[laughter] but I know I'm probably going
to make you laugh because I made my
daughter laugh today. That my first
human thought is like, "Wow,
you really need to go to therapy for
that, isn't it?" And they're in therapy.
I'm the therapist, but the situation is
so like that's my first and then I'm
like, "Oh, yeah, what am I saying?" And
then I, you know, I I I then I start and
I start to, you know, do some work. But
my first initial thought is that why am
I saying that? Because I feel like for
men it's like
there it's like when when you when
there's hard times, there's not enough
money in the family or the you know
there's things going on in just whatever
and the man is supposed to take care of
it. I can imagine how lonely that can
feel for some, you know, for some men in
certain situations because you are the
you are the the therapist. you're the
one that's supposed to be able to fix it
or help or whatever and you're feeling
like emotionally overwhelmed. I just
compare it to that. Like even though
we're I know for myself I'm a mental
health professional and I and I, you
know, know that I am trained to be able
to help in so many different situations,
but sometimes the situations seem so
overwhelming that I'm just like, you
need to get help. Oh, that's what
they're here for. So I feel like men may
go through that at times where
do they feel like they have somebody
else because it's almost like the buck
stops here. You are that person
>> that can be very challenging and
stressful even though there's God that
you can depend upon God. Hopefully
you're in a healthy relationship with
you know with a sp with your wife that
they're here to support you. I'm hoping
that you have all of those things. you
always have God, but maybe you don't
have a relationship with God in that
way. So, you're not automatically
calling upon him. And maybe you don't
have that relationship with a wife that
>> supports you. Maybe you're always
feeling torn down. That's the other
thing. That's why I'm glad women are
here. I'm seeing a lot of men, but I
hope women are here. We can be we can
um not help sometimes in that when we're
always snipping and pulling. They have a
lot. I know we go through a lot as
women. Trust me, I'm team women all the
time. I understand what our what we go
through, but they go through a lot, too.
>> Go through a lot, too. And we can either
help or make that worse.
>> Mercy. Mercy. Please don't make it
worse. Uh, let's
>> It's better for me to say it than you,
Dr. White.
>> Oh, 100%. 100%. I I kind of stayed
clear.
>> I went to Clint. Clint's got a
statement. So, we need to identify the
problem and the processes of conflict
resolution.
Yeah. Um I think I probably asked you
this before because now he's talking
about conflict resolution. How many
physical fights have you been in in your
life?
>> Me?
>> Yeah. Physical fights.
>> Zero. [laughter]
>> Zero.
>> That's how peaceful Dante is. I can. No,
I can. I my my mouth is like I can I can
like say a whole bunch of stuff, but
I've like I was never gonna get in a
physical fight. That's why I always tell
my husband because he's been in so many
and I'm like, "You're not you weren't
scared?" Like what? No. He's like, "You
don't have time to be scared. You just
I'm like, you're just going to like
punch somebody in their face? Like
what?" I mean, this is before he found
God, but I'm just saying.
>> Anyways, I couldn't do that. But go
ahead. Well, but it's interesting
because do you know what the average is
like? And obviously there's folk there's
outliers like Pastor Meyers, [laughter]
but he's an outlier.
>> He's the average number is like two to
three. That's the average number. Two to
three. So over the course of your life,
again, like don't don't think about
these folk who like frequent bars and
they're always in fights. No, I'm
talking about just the average. you're
typically going to have two to three
fights over the course of a lifetime.
Now, in contrast to that, and and think
about how much preparation
uh people
engage in to prepare for that fight
that's never going to take place, right?
All these gyms and UFC gyms and karate
this and taekwondo this and dojo this
and you know, and your husband is
trained if I'm not mistaken, right?
>> Yeah.
In contrast to that,
>> how many verbal fights have you been in?
>> Oh, now that
>> so you you know what the average is? So
the average is that you'll get into
about 2500
verbal fights over the course of a 70
year lifespan. 2500.
>> I calculated those up pretty quick if
before I knew Jesus. For sure.
[laughter]
You rack you racked those up and maybe
you're like going back to the norm now.
But
>> I was always so quick with the tongue.
Anyway, God is, you know, God is good.
[clears throat]
>> He's good. Well, well, but we put so
little effort into sharpening our
communication skills because Clint was
asking about was talking about the
importance of conflict resolution. And
what I'm championing is these are some
of the skills you will gain from
therapy. Good therapy anyway because I'm
sure sister Atante always talks about
for example a u a slow startup. What is
it?
>> A slow startup.
>> A slow startup. Sorry. A soft startup.
Yes.
>> A soft startup. And soft startup.
>> Yeah. Like always like how do you do a
soft startup?
>> But these are tools.
>> Like these are tools that absolutely
when you master them they make life
easier. So
>> yeah, so your thing about conflict
resolution
um yeah, we got to identify the problem
and the process of conflict resolution
and sharpen our skills in the area of um
conflict resolution.
>> Yes,
>> brother Tennessee,
>> we got a great question. It says, "What
does a healed man look like mentally?"
>> Brother,
>> from day to day, is there a finish line?
Great question.
>> If there was merch, man, you would have
just won a t-shirt. Oh man, that's such
a good question. What does a heal
>> heel man look like?
>> Well, you know, brother Tennessee,
I think that was the whole point that
was the whole point of scripture. That
was a whole like I promise you I'm not
trying to overspiritualize it, but like
I think I think the whole point of the
New Testament, the Old Testament, but
like that buildup to Christ was I'm
going to show you a picture of a healed
man. I'm going to show you what that
looks like. I'm going to show you the
person that can steal the waves, that
can deal with the demoniac, but children
are attracted to be around. This is the
person who created the Leviathan, but
he's still gentle enough to where
children want to gather around him. And
and I think sometimes that's the
struggle. Uh, Brother Tennessee, like um
we can be dominant,
but everybody's afraid of us. Um, or or
other times, you know, you get other you
can get to the other extreme now where
you're so gentle, you don't inspire
anybody with a sense of comfort and a
sense that no, that person would defend
me if necessary.
>> And so that's where you have to blend
the two. You can't people can't be
terrified of you but they also still
need to fear you and respect you at the
same time. There's this balance.
>> Um so uh brother Tennessee a healed man
is an integrated man.
>> Uh a healed man understands balance and
here's the key and can and can deliver
the appropriate picture of masculinity
>> depending on the setting.
>> Yes. And you can see why you need God to
guide that. Like they they deliver just
the right amount of masculinity to the
given setting. What were you gonna say,
sis?
>> I was just going to say a healed man
also is not afraid to show his emotions
if he's if he's hurting um or if he if
he want if he needs to cry. A healed man
is is is okay with crying and knowing
that that's not that does not equal
weakness. It actually can equal
strength.
Um, just because you're able to show
emotion and you're not ashamed of it.
>> Now, feel free to balance that because
you and I both know women don't like a
man who cries too much.
>> Well, balance it. Not Right. Right. I
agree. I agree. But, you know, to be
honest, I mean, that might mean might be
my own personal preference.
>> No, no, no, no, no. This is all women.
Like,
>> well, you know, Ricardo, I don't know
all women. [laughter]
>> I know, I know, I know, I know, I know,
I know. But I just, as a as a as a
brother out there, let me spare you like
because like I'm sorry, it is an ugly
truth, but it is a truth. You can lose
points for crying too much. Um
>> yes I mean you can listen
>> if um
>> dep depending on the circumstance. I
mean honestly but if but it's really
healthy like I just don't think we
should perpetuate that
not healthy narrative that's so heavy
already in society where men just don't
like if you want to cry cry. Why?
Because God gave you the tears. Now you
don't I mean nobody wants a too weepy of
a woman or too weepy of a man mean like
where you're crying all the time. Every
single thing makes you cry. Well, no.
That's probably that's unhealthy.
>> That's true.
>> So we know healthy crying and not
healthy crying. I think our natural
instincts we kind of understand and pick
that up.
>> Does that make sense?
>> Okay. Well, and and let me let me tell
you what I'm what I'm balancing it with.
Like
>> guys, ladies, cry all that you need. All
I'm saying is my trick is I cry in
private, you know. So, when I need to
emit some tears or whatever, the shower
is a great place, you know, and
>> add to the water.
>> I tend to I tend to reserve my tears for
the shower and the pillow, you know. I
like privacy, you know. Um, so and as
I'm not your mental health professional,
but I think [laughter]
I think that I mean that is your
personality type which is fine if if
that's fine. But I think if we put that
like on everybody then then that
probably wouldn't be healthy. Like I
think
>> of course of course I mean like Yeah.
But but but but believe it or not, I'm
trying to not I'm trying to do like that
thing where you make therapy safe where
it's like I I will prepare you for the
real world. And that is as much as in
therapy I would love to tell you cry to
your heart's content,
>> right?
>> I just understand you can lose points
for that. Um, and and
>> I think if you're crying and the te and
I don't know, we're sticking on this
crying thing just for but I think if
you're crying and and it's isolated and
you're always just crying, that's where
I think a woman would be annoyed or
whatever. But if you are showing
maturity and working hard trying to make
all of these things work when you're
just like, you know what, I'm at that
point where I just need to let some
tears out. And if you're I feel like
it's a lot of stress if you feel like I
got to wait till I get in the shower or
I got to wait till I see my pillow. But
you know what I'm saying? Like if I'm at
a funeral right now,
>> right? If I'm at a funeral, it comes
out. It comes out. You know, I'm at a
funeral. What do you want me to do? You
know what I'm saying? [laughter]
You know, so
>> guys, we need a therapist for Dr. White.
And I
[laughter]
of course at a funeral you're going to
cry. But I'm just talking about in life
in general. I You know why I'm so kind
of passionate about this, Dr. White?
Because men just if if they just feel
like if they feel guarded and I like I
just have to watch this and I can't let
this emotion out. They already have a
hard time letting the emotions out. So I
just don't want to put any limitations
on them. I think if they are again being
good, not just crying, but being good
men and working hard and you know trying
to provide and do all these other
things, putting like the majority of the
men here are Christians, putting God
first in their life and their women see
all of this and it's like it's almost um
it's a good look for that man to the
woman to see that you're doing all of
these things and you can share shed some
tears. or share your emotions and you're
not too
um
prideful, not just prideful, but not too
afraid to show it because a lot of times
it's not prideful, it's just like you're
like afraid to show you're going to look
think you're looking weak. If if they
feel comfortable um and strong enough to
do that because they're so manly in so
many other areas, I think it's okay to
cry whenever you need to cry. So, um,
just so you guys don't think I'm the
brute that Sister Tant is making me out
to be, right? Talking about I need a
therapist. Um,
we need a therapist for us today. No,
>> he's not a brute at all. You're great,
Dr. White.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
>> We're human. We have different opinions.
Okay.
>> Well, well, what I'm what I'm trying to
protect against is here's what I'm
trying to protect against this. So here
we are inviting these men to open up
their hearts and to be vulnerable. And
sis, I cannot put into words the pain of
when you make yourself vulnerable and
it's weaponized against you.
>> Right. I
devastating. That is
>> I've I've seen that happen many times
with relationship.
>> So that's that's what I'm balancing
where it's like if I'm challenging you
to be vulnerable, I do have to add that
word of caution that I cannot assume you
are in a setting where your
vulnerability will be honored,
>> right?
>> And and I'm saying there are settings
that will misunderstand it and may even
weaponize it. But to a sister Atante's
point, you've got to find settings to
let it out productively,
>> right? And you know, we're kind of
focusing on this crying part, but really
also a big huge thing is for men to feel
safe to be able to just communicate
period. Like just to talk like what's on
your heart. You don't even have to cry.
just just to let somebody in to see what
you're really feeling because men just
shut down. I mean, women, we can shut
down, too, but I just think that wall
for men goes up so quick. It's like it
be I mean, our walls go up, but we're
more of
uh we don't want to talk it out in a
healthy way. We want to
>> duke it out. Well,
>> we're going to verbally duke it out. And
men just shut down. They'll be like,
"Okay." like they're not trying to meet
our energy in the same way. They're
meeting our energy, but in a passive
aggressive walls gone up, I've totally
tuned you out. Um I think um Gotman
would say stonewalling,
>> right? Well, well, like I think the
scary part of it is when you don't even
know your man's checked out. Like
>> right,
>> you you you don't even know they've
checked out, but they have deemed you
unsafe. And they don't even have
language for this. They don't have
language for this. But the bottom line
is,
>> sis, if if they could articulate it,
they would let you know, I feel like
you're unsafe. They But when have you
ever heard a man talk like that? I feel
like you're unsafe.
>> They wouldn't It's very rare that
they're going to say that, but their
reaction is telling you that shutting
down,
>> which you might not even perceive. they
might play along and make you think
everything's okay and suddenly there's a
collapse somewhere else,
>> right?
>> Um and so so that's why this
conversation I think is is just so
important. Um one of the other things is
all of this stuff that we're talking
about with the stigma and the difficulty
communicating it has profound
>> epidemiological and statistical
outcomes. Meaning men are more likely to
die by suicide compared to women.
>> Yes.
>> So now women attempt more, but men are
more more likely to actually die. So
what we're talking about has real
consequences.
>> It it really does. It really really
does. And so thank you for bringing that
out. Um because
like you said, women, we let it out.
They'll be like, "What? We're just we're
chatty, right? I mean, we're quick to
just even if we don't do it in a healthy
way, we're still letting it out. Um, men
will will keep it in and keep it in. And
when they attempt to unalive themselves,
um, they want to make sure that they get
the job done, unfortunately. Um, and so
they'll use, um, as you know, a lot of
times it's it's a gun,
um, or something like that. um because
they don't the taking the pills and the
stuff that that that that may not work.
You know, that's how a lot of men think.
And so definitely men are statistically
there's a higher rate of men that
actually women attempt but men get it
done. And so that's why we have to check
in on the men that we love in this
world. And I'm not just talking about
your spouse, talking about your son,
your brother,
um your father, you know, I mean, you
have to check in because men are not
telling you everything that they're
feeling. You really don't know. And
they're good at covering it up.
>> Yeah.
>> A lot of times.
>> Powerful. That's powerful.
>> Some a lot of times we're just so
shocked like he did what? Um and we did
a show on it. We did not a show. It's
not a show, but we did an episode, I
should say, on it. Um, I'm forgetting
his name. He was the dancer for
>> Well, I'm sorry.
>> Oh, the dancer
>> for Ellen when Ellen Degenerous.
>> I remember that. I remember that.
>> I can't remember.
>> He's very well known. Him and his wife
did a lot of social media dances
together and stuff like that. And I'm
forgetting his name, but people were
shocked.
Yes, Stitch. Thank you, Ammer Stitch. Uh
people were shocked
>> when that happened, but his wife knew a
little bit of what he was going through.
And I say a little bit, she didn't know
the depths of how deep it was. I think
she's written a book now, but that is
not an isolated story for sure,
>> but it it brings it all full circle
because we can put on such a phenomenal
game face.
>> We can we are we are so conditioned to
keep you out.
Like one of the things I love about
driving is I can I can use my real face.
Like I don't have to use a face that
would make someone say, "Hey, what's
wrong?" You know, I can just wear
whatever face I want, you know? So what
if the person across is thinking, "Oh,
that guy looks angry. I can just be who
I want to be,
>> right?
>> And and not have my experience be
intruded upon." Um but yes, we are so
good at putting on, you know, this face
and it can have dire consequences.
>> So, you know, if you're a man or if you
are a woman who loves a man,
>> um this episode is for you and this
episode is encouragement that we want
you to know that one of the most
powerful signs of strength is getting
the help you need.
>> Right. Right. Absolutely. And I know,
you know, we're um we're not quite at
the end. We're almost to the end. So,
put your questions in u and your
comments, but I'm already really because
we see I a lot of men the uh I asked the
pray the men's group to to announce that
we're doing this topic and I feel like a
lot of them are here and uh I feel like
we could definitely
>> do a part two part two next week as
well.
>> No question. No question
>> because this is I don't want to just
this is just something that we just
don't talk about enough
>> enough. Clint said can work or exercise
be a healthy outlet for those emotional
struggles.
So Clint what do you you want to take it
sis?
>> Well I'll just say this definitely
exercise is a healthy um is a healthy
outlet. Um I'll let you take work. I go
ahead. But I don't think the other
outlet, but go ahead.
>> Well, well, there's a thing anytime I
say the word stress or when you usually
hear the word stress, we think about it
in a negative context, right?
>> So, but really what we're associating
with the stress is distress.
>> Yes.
>> Um there's another form of stress called
ustress. Ustress is good stress. So like
take work for example. When I have all
the resources I need to do my job in
excellence, that's ustress. That's not a
burden. That's a delight.
>> Right.
>> Okay. And it is it is and it is a coping
mechanism. It's it it does feel good to
engage in activity where I feel like I'm
making a difference. I'm doing it at the
high level and I've got all the
resources I need. But yeah, work can
then become distressful if there are
challenges being imposed on me where I
don't feel like I have the adequate
resources. I'm not given enough time to
hit the deadlines that I need to hit.
I'm not given the resources I need for
whatever reason. Now, it's going from
ustress to distress,
>> right?
>> But when it's ustress, it can be a way
to cope. But I think what Sister Tante
is warning against is sometimes when we
become almost like workaholics
>> and work becomes an escape from dealing
with the issues you need to deal with.
>> Now we got a problem. Now we got a
problem. So So I I I think it can be a
good thing but it can also be um used as
escape. And you guys know what else is
used as escape right? Addictions.
Addictions really provide an escape and
that's why it's so important to actually
address the issues that need to be
addressed rather than being dominated by
them.
>> Right. Yes. And I think since I mean we
just need to do a series a a men's
series and this is number one. This is
the first episode because as you're
talking I'm you guys are you are in our
planning session. We're doing it live.
But when you're saying that and you
brought up addiction, I think it's
important when you're talking about
men's mental health. How can we not talk
about pornography
>> and that's
>> so Yeah,
>> that'll be a part of the whole picture
because that can play such a huge part.
>> Absolutely. And it almost like deserves
its own like special focus in terms of
pornography. Like
>> it's definitely going to have its own
episode. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Yeah. if not one or two or three.
I mean, because it's such a huge thing.
And, you know, just to be fair, it's not
just uh a male problem.
>> It's not a male. It's not just a male
problem
>> at all. Uh women deal with um the
addiction as well.
>> Absolutely.
>> Um so, it looks like we have some more.
Let's see. Take a few more questions.
Does a man's upbringing affect him as
far um as like expressing his emotions?
Because most households, especially in
the 70s and 80s, boys couldn't express
themselves and were taught to hold it
in. Absolutely. And that's what we were
talking about with society. Society has
trained our men, especially during that
time. I mean, now it's getting a little
bit better. I think this generation,
these last two generations, they're
definitely open to um
men expressing themsel more in a healthy
way, letting their emotions actually
going into counseling and therapy.
There's not such a taboo and a stigma
behind that. It's getting better. It
still can get much, much better, but
it's been exactly how you described it
um in your question
um for so many years and so long. It has
definitely uh affected uh the men in our
society today for sure in all cultures.
I think it's across the board. Um I will
say it's in all cultures. Uh but I'm
just thinking of my dad. Um and I just
remember him not really feeling
comfortable. like he showed me that he
loved me and my brother and those type
of things. But when it was a hard
situation, those were difficult for him.
He wasn't I could now being as a mental
health therapist, I can look back um he
definitely it wasn't like he didn't deal
with it or talk to it, but he never
really wanted he didn't you can tell he
really did not enjoy that and he didn't
really know how to communicate or open
up. So he would avoid or ignore certain
situations cuz he just didn't really
hadn't learned those tools as a young
>> like he didn't want to say I love you or
something or
>> Oh no. And he he definitely said that
and showed me I felt and showed me and
my brother and my children he loved me
so much I was very spoiled. Okay, let's
just put it that way. It was like it was
like my mom will tell you she was just
like you spoiled this girl too much. But
so I definitely felt love. So, not that
I'm saying like when difficult
situations
happened, he would try to just not take
that deep dive into it to be like, let's
unpack this. Let's, you know, he he just
wanted to be like, all right, let's just
move on, you know, because he didn't
want to touch those difficult uh
emotions. So, and it wasn't just with
me. It was
>> in a lot of situations.
>> I felt
>> man, but I know that came from his
upbringing. Um,
yeah.
>> Well,
>> my grandfather who wasn't emotionally
present, he was an alcoholic. So, I
think that's where it came from.
>> Well, it's profound because I know I'm
from the generation of be seen and not
heard.
>> Oh, for sure.
>> You know, be seen and not heard. And so,
of course, my parenting was a reaction
against that. So, I wanted my daughter
uh be seen and be heard. Well, she took
it to a little extreme. We're We're
trying to like get back to that
generation of
don't be quite so hard. I'm joking. I'm
joking, of course. But like she's off
the chain like no, I'm going to be
heard. Um
>> but it was a reaction against this whole
>> wait, why wouldn't you value that
person? Like why wouldn't you
communicate? No, you're valued. You're
human. you know, so
>> but but and you can see if your emphasis
is on being quiet, then you're not
really attuning to what's going on with
you. You're more just so focused
outward, you might not be paying
attention to what's going on inside. And
then and then as men, we don't like
dealing with things. We don't like
asking questions we don't have answers
for.
>> We're just like, I just leave it alone.
Like if if I'm going to ask a I need an
answer. And so much of mental health has
to deal with that. Well, these are not
clear concrete, you know,
>> answers to questions like looking at a
circuit breaker or
the the worlds we often like to operate
in. No, this is a bit more amorphous,
but the work is still rewarding. It's
still rewarding. [clears throat] Also um
something like that I see like with when
I'm working with couples um is like you
know the women can just rattle I mean we
as women we can just rattle off facts
our memory is like you know we can just
say you know this happened this happened
this is how I feel this is you know we
just process things can process things
so quickly like as we're already done
processing the situation like like
within seconds or you know a few seconds
the man's thoughts are just loading and
he's just like just trying to like let
me process it and like we try to as
women we want to rush their process get
mad when they're processing service or
server or whatever and their brain is
not going as fast as ours and then that
makes them want to shut down even more.
So you don't get
anything out of them because
the wall just went up because they were
just traumatized because they couldn't
process it and it was just like they
just shut down and they just give up.
>> Let me let me let me just say it
concretely. Um, ladies, it is sometimes
easy for you to bully us verbally
because you're more conversant
>> because your command of language at
times is a bit more sophisticated.
So it doesn't mean it doesn't mean
you're more sophisticated,
but your your capacity with language is
more sophisticated and it positions you
to bully us verbally.
>> Let me say
>> I I I just Yeah, you said bully us, but
you know, I guess that's the you
sometimes that's the right terminology.
I I can't I can't uh I can't defend us
ladies because sometimes we are
definitely in that space and category.
What I was told and you're the doctor.
>> Put a one in the chat if I'm speaking
the truth. Go ahead.
Go ahead. Go ahead.
>> I think um you know that we have the
able like communication on both on the
left and right hemisphere of the brain.
Is that correct doctor?
>> Yeah. You you go between both
hemispheres.
>> We can just be like boom boom boom boom
boom. Where you guys don't have it on
both.
>> We focus we focus more on our I'm
pointing my right but like yeah we we
focus more on our left hemisphere. We
prefer left hemispheral thinking which
is more concrete, which is more
engineering. The right hemisphere is
more artistic. It's more big picture,
>> right?
>> Um, and you're seeing women like you see
the word for I would say is integrated.
Like they love going between both.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, there's an attacker, but he's he's
someone's child. Whereas a man, it's
like we kind of have an easier time now
just zeroing in and saying, I don't care
that but he's an attacker,
>> right? Um, but no, you you do go between
they're they're different styles of
thinking.
>> Yes. No. Right. It it makes it makes
sense. I know that like I will be so
focused on all the little details and
just like right in the moment of things
and then my husband is silent. He
doesn't he didn't he doesn't say
anything and then when he speaks it's
like he's definitely looking at big
picture and you know going beyond just
the little moment and I'm like I wasn't
even thinking about that at all.
>> [laughter]
>> I wasn't even
>> No, but I I got to give you props for
the details. It's like he's like all
like like deep and whatever, but like
your command of just the landscape. Hey,
but don't forget about this date and
don't forget and what about this? And
I'm like that's dope. [laughter] It's
like the the marriage is dope. So, you
got one that like he's down, you know,
but like you're like, let me keep you
oriented.
>> Yeah. Sometimes I tell them I was like
you're
you're out here in space [laughter] and
like we're on the floor we're on we're
in earth trying to like and you're over
here play anyway. So yeah I think we
compliment each other for sure
beautifully.
>> Yeah for sure.
>> He balances me and I hope by God's grace
I balance him as well. This has been you
know I have to give it to you Dr. White.
This was Dr. White's idea to do men and
we really have so much more to talk
about men's mental health. There's so
much more guys that we can go and so
we're taking this deep dive and I can
see like and thank you for all all there
I see there's a lot more men this
evening showing up. I think it's great.
I'm definitely going to be pushing to
encourage women to show up too for this
next set for these next uh few weeks
because we need to hear this. We need to
understand
uh the men that we are either raising or
married to or dating, whatever the case
may be. Uh we need to understand um what
men go through so we can be helpful.
>> You know, I would love to take all the
credit for this because it would just
feel so good. I gotta shout out Denise
Richardson for giving me the idea. Shout
out Denise. I don't know if you're
watching or whatever.
>> I don't know if Denise is on this
evening. I haven't seen her, but
>> but like props. She's she is the one.
And so and and and I just think as men
it it can be
>> I didn't know it was a woman. I'm just
kidding. [laughter]
>> I'm just kidding.
>> That's why we don't say.
>> No, I'm just kidding. You could have
just kept I'm sure Denise wouldn't have
minded, but no, that that's great.
>> Just I just got to give props where it's
due because I think as men that's one of
the things that's it's important that we
do is yo man, if if you have a woman
supporting you, providing shout it out.
>> Yes. You know, so props.
>> Definitely. And thank you, Sister Tante,
for uh for
>> disturbing. You know, I can I can give
you this. You were wise enough to listen
to the woman's idea.
>> I will take that.
>> Yes, you deserve it. You deserve it.
This is a definitely a good topic. I
like to see again all the men and the
sprinkles of women, but we want I want
more women and more men next week
because I think it's an awesome topic
that we all need to it's a critical
topic that uh everyone needs to hear.
Let's go out with this question. My
testosterone levels are high. A couple
of different reasons. How can I keep
myself in check, but yet also try to be
a good person. For example, I curse a
lot. My friend, the physician that
you're really going to want to help you
as far as testosterone levels is is
oftentimes a urologist. Um, so you
you're definitely going to want that,
you know, managed by urologist. So
you'll often sometimes have to get a
referral from your primary care doctor
to your urologist and have that uh
monitored and managed. Um but these are
important things. These are really
really important things that can help
manage it. And then once that medical
stuff is clear, then you can then talk
to a therapist, a coach, a practitioner
to help you
find more effective ways of
communicating in a way that will get you
what you want without having to
necessarily rely, for example, on
cursing. So, you know, I applaud you for
asking that question.
>> I do too.
>> Um, and having the courage to say, "Hey,
man, I need help." [clears throat]
>> That's right. Absolutely.
>> So, over to you, sis. Yeah, this was
this was epic. And invite your the
invite the men and women who love them.
>> Yes, please. Please uh definitely invite
them. We will do a part two. This is a
series now. It's starting to become a
series. Uh we will be here next week uh
same time, same YouTube channel. So,
definitely invite them. And then please
share this link. Invite them. But share
that. Let them know what they missed.
they can see it and then they will uh
we'll be able to build on more next
week. So, we look forward to seeing all
of you here for mental health Monday
next week. Thank you for being here this
evening. Um and have a good rest of your
evening. See you next